A Guide to the Charles Walls Collection, 1882-2003
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Charles Walls Collection, 1882-2003
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2011-001
1.5 cu. ft. 3 boxes
Photocopies of magazine articles and other sources relating to the Civil War, with particular emphases on Long Island, New York during the war, African-American history, and the Ku Klux Klan.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Charles Walls Collection was donated to Special Collections in 2006.
Biographical Note
Charles Sebastian Walls III, a resident of Blacksburg, Virginia and a Civil War enthusiast, was born in Oceanside, New York, on October 15, 1934. A master gardener and retired truck driver, Walls died on December 17, 2008.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains photocopies and other reproductions of Civil War-related magazine articles and other sources compiled by Charles Walls, a resident of Blacksburg, Virginia and a Civil War enthusiast. The collection, which contains only a few original items, reveals a general interest in the Civil War and its various aspects. The collection's most significant contents, perhaps, are several files on the Ku Klux Klan and related organizations, with articles tracing the Klan's origin and history as well as its activities through the 1990s. The collection also includes a number of articles relating to African-American history and the Civil Rights movement. Other files relate to the preservation of Confederate heritage and include articles surrounding the Confederate battle flag and other controversial issues. Many of these items seem not to have been gathered firsthand by Walls but given to him by another party. The collection also emphasizes the Civil War as it related to Long Island, New York, with articles on military units, events, and individuals.
Arrangement
The collection essentially retains its original order and is arranged alphabetically by subject.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Separated Materials
The following books were removed from the collection and cataloged for the Rare Book Collection:
The 119th New York Vols. and Their Participation in the Gettysburg Campaign June 12, 1863 to July 4, 1863 ([S.l.: s.n., 1986]). E523.5 119th W45 1986 Civil War Spec
Hartwig, D. Scott and Ann Marie Hartwig, Gettysburg: the Complete Pictorial of Battlefield Monuments (Gettysburg, PA: Thomas Publications, 1995). E475.56 H37 1995 Civil War Spec
Index Terms
Subjects:
Ku Klux Klan (1915- ); Ku Klux Klan (19th cent.)
Local Subjects:
Civil War
Contents List
- Arkansas, n.d. (Box-folder 1-1)
- Battlefield parks and trails, 1995-1998, n.d. (Box-folder 1-2)
- Black history, 1916-1991, n.d., [2 folders] (Box-folder 1-3)
- Black history - Civil War, 1918-1990, n.d., [2 folders] (Box-folder 1-4)
- Black history - New York, 1917-1993, n.d., [2 folders] (Box-folder 1-5)
- "The Civil War" (PBS mini-series), 1990. (Box-folder 1-6)
- Confederate battle flag, 1990-1997, n.d. (Box-folder 1-7)
- Copperheads, 1935, n.d. (Box-folder 1-8)
- CSS Hunley, 1995-1999, n.d. (Box-folder 1-9)
- Espionage, 1986-1989, n.d. (Box-folder 1-10)
- Florida, 2001, n.d. (Box-folder 1-11)
- Foreign involvement, 1984-1996, n.d. (Box-folder 1-12)
- Georgia, 1986-1996, n.d. (Box-folder 1-13)
- Gettysburg, 1983-2000, n.d. (Box-folder 1-14)
- Ku Klux Klan, 1901-1995, n.d., [3 folders] (Box-folder 2-1)
- Ku Klux Klan - Long Island, New York, 1921-1992, n.d. (Box-folder 2-2)
- Leaders, Confederate, 1956-1986, n.d. (Box-folder 2-3)
- Leaders, Union, 1970-1997, n.d. (Box-folder 2-4)
- Long Island, New York, 1882-1996, n.d., [3 folders] (Box-folder 2-5)
- Louisiana, 1995-1997, n.d. (Box-folder 2-6)
- Maine, 1994, n.d. (Box-folder 2-7)
- Maryland, 1986-1995, n.d. (Box-folder 2-8)
- Mississippi, n.d. (Box-folder 2-9)
- Missouri, 1985-1994, n.d. (Box-folder 2-10)
- Naval operations, 1984-1999, n.d. (Box-folder 3-1)
- New Jersey, 1995, n.d. (Box-folder 3-2)
- New York, 1924-1996, n.d., [2 folders] (Box-folder 3-3)
- North Carolina, 1995, n.d. (Box-folder 3-4)
- Nursing, 1995, n.d. (Box-folder 3-5)
- Prisoners of war, 1984-1996, n.d. (Box-folder 3-6)
- Reconstruction, 1974, n.d. (Box-folder 3-7)
- South Carolina, 1927-1966, n.d. (Box-folder 3-8)
- Southern heritage, n.d. (Box-folder 3-9)
- Tennessee, 1984-2000, n.d. (Box-folder 3-10)
- Texas, 1987-2001, n.d. (Box-folder 3-11)
- Vermont, 1976-1989. (Box-folder 3-12)
- Veterans, 1959-1996, n.d. (Box-folder 3-13)
- Virginia battles A-M, 1984-2001, n.d. (Box-folder 3-14)
- Virginia battles, N-Z, 1987-2003, n.d. (Box-folder 3-15)
- Virginia Center for Civil War Studies, 1998-2001, n.d. (Box-folder 3-16)
- Virginia, Southwest, 1988-1999, n.d. (Box-folder 3-17)
- Warfare and weaponry, 1988-1996, n.d. (Box-folder 3-18)
- West Virginia, 1985-1995, n.d. (Box-folder 3-19)
- Western theater, 1989-1995, n.d. (Box-folder 3-20)